Guide to the Charles Hazen Blood Papers, 1889-1909
Blood, Charles Hazen papers, 1889-1909
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Charles Hazen Blood papers, 1889-1909
2263
Charles Hazen Blood, 1866-1938.
3.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence, depositions and other legal documents, statements of account, memoranda, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, depositions and other legal documents, statements of account, and memoranda, mainly concerning legal matters Blood handled in public office and in private practice, as well as his family and personal business affairs. Also documented are Blood's activities as a Cornell alumnus, mainly regarding the promotion and financing of Alumni Field and his candidacy for reelection as alumni trustee in 1906, as graduate treasurer of the Cornell Masque, and as an alumnus and supporter of Kappa Alpha fraternity; and his activities as an Ithaca landlord, developer of Cornell Heights and Cayuga Heights, supporter of the Ithaca Conservatory of Music (now Ithaca College), and Presbyterian layman.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lawyer, district attorney, 1895-1903, and county judge and surrogate of Tompkins County, New York, 1904-1907; Cornell University trustee, 1901-1924; director of local corporations and bank official.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, depositions and other legal documents, statements of account, and memoranda, mainly concerning legal matters Blood handled in public office and in private practice, as well as his family and personal business affairs. Included are letters, photographs, and other papers dealing with liquor and gambling law violations; extradition proceedings and other aspects of civil and criminal cases; the settlement of estates, farm mortgage holdings and family properties in Kansas, Nebraska, and North and South Dakota and investments in Pitkin County, Colorado, bonds, and litigation over oil property in Titusville, Pennsylvania in which his father had invested; the visit of the Imperial Chinese Commissioners, 1906; his work as director and chairman of the executive committee of the Ithaca, New York, Telephone Company, much of which is concerned with its competition with the Bell System, and with the management of the Caroline Telephone Company and the Trumbull's Corners Telephone Company; his work as attorney for the Ithaca Street Railway, involving in part the choice of a route across the Cornell campus and the promotion of connecting electric lines; his interest in state and local Republican politics and such related matters as appointments and elections to the State Supreme Court and the selection of the site for a new post office building in Ithaca.
Also documented are Blood's activities as a Cornell alumnus, mainly regarding the promotion and financing of Alumni Field and his candidacy for reelection as alumni trustee in 1906, as graduate treasurer of the Cornell Masque, and as an alumnus and supporter of Kappa Alpha fraternity; and his activities as an Ithaca landlord, developer of Cornell Heights and Cayuga Heights, supporter of the Ithaca Conservatory of Music (now Ithaca College), and Presbyterian layman. Includes papers of Charles F. Blood. Correspondents include George W. Bacon, Fred D. Barto, W. D. Barnard, Herman Bergholtz, Romeyn Berry, Charles D. Bostwick, Herman V. Bostwick, Charles D. Coburn, T. F. Crane, Hollis E. Dann, Harry F. Dixie, John Wilbur Dwight, Albert F. Gladding, Samuel Grumbine, Henry Gaines Hawn, Hervey C. Hazen, David N. Heller, Frank H. Hiscock, Bert G. Hubbell, Horace Mack, Burr Mattice, Jared T. Newman, Cuthbert W. Pound, George Priest, George W. Ray, Willard W. Rowlee, Henry W. Sackett, Jacob Gould Schurman, John L. Senior, Edwin C. Stewart, Charles M. Titus, Charles E. Treman, Sr., Robert H. Treman, Henry A. Van Alstyne, Mynderse Van Cleef, Andrew S. White, Ernest I. White, Frederick J. Whiton, Emmons L. Williams, George R. Williams, Roger B. Williams, Clarence F. Wyckoff, and Edward G. Wyckoff.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Blood, Charles Hazen, 1866-1938.; Blood, Charles F.; Bacon, George Washington, 1830-1921.; Barto, Fred D.; Bergholtz, Herman.; Berry, Romeyn, 1881-1957.; Bostwick, Charles Dibble, 1870-1937.; Bostwick, Herman V.; Coburn, Charles D.; Crane, T. F.; Dann, Hollis E.; Dixie, Harry F.; Dwight, John Wilbur.; Gladding, Albert F.; Grumbine, Samuel.; Hawn, Henry Gaines.; Hazen, Hervey Crosby.; Heller, David N.; Hiscock, Frank H.; Hubbell, Bert G.; Mack, Horace.; Mattice, Burr.; Newman, Jared T. (Jared Treman), 1855-1937.; Pound, Cuthbert Winfred, 1864-1935.; Priest, George.; Ray, George W.; Rowlee, Willard W.; Sackett, Henry W.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Senior, John L.; Stewart, Edwin C.; Titus, Charles M.; Treman, Charles E., Sr.; Treman, Robert H. (Robert Henry), 1858-1937.; Van Alstyne, Henry A.; Van Cleef, Mynderse.; White, Andrew S.; White, Ernest I.; Whiton, Frederick J.; Williams, Emmons L.; Williams, George Robert.; Williams, Roger B.; Wyckoff, Clarence F.; Wyckoff, Edward G.; Cornell University.; Ithaca Telephone Company.; Caroline Telephone Company.; Trumbull's Corners Telephone Company.; Ithaca Street Railway.; Ithaca College.
Subjects:
Land use--Kansas.; Land use--Nebraska.; Land use--North Dakota.; Land use--South Dakota.; Practice of law.; Finance.; Investments.; City planning.; Regional planning.; Lawyers.; Judges.; Bankers.
Places:
Cayuga Heights (N.Y.)--City planning.; Cornell Heights (Ithaca, N.Y.)--City planning.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; Ithaca (N.Y.)--City planning.; Pitkin County (Colo.); Titusville (Pa.); China--Foreign relations.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Charles F. Blood
Boxes 1-6
Series II. Charles H. Blood
Boxes 7-11
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Charles F. Blood
  - Correspondence and other manuscript items
    - 1842-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1860-1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes letters ( Dec. 1861 ) from a member of one of the Union army's bands; letters address the condition of the army, gives battle descriptions and speaks about "Balls Bluff"
    - 1863-July 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes letters ( May 1863, May 1864, June 1864, July 6, 1864, July 30, 1864 ) from John Barnard, a soldier in the Union army; letters address the Battle of Chancellorsville, the experiences of a man who was held prisoner by the Confederates, conditions in the South, General Sherman, and the anticipation of an attack on Atlanta
    - Aug. 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes letters ( Aug. 1864, Sept. 1864 ) written by Barnard outside of Atlanta and then in Atlanta; letters address the soldier's hope for Lincoln's reelection, his desire for the war's end, his anticipation of an attack on Atlanta, and then finally a description of the Yankee seizure of Atlanta
    - 1866-June 1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - July 1869-1870 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1871 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes insurance contracts for the various properties that Blood owned and for the First Presbyterian Church in Ithaca for which Blood was a trustee
    - 1872-Feb. 1873 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes insurance contracts for the various properties that Blood owned and for the First Presbyterian Church in Ithaca
    - Mar. 1873-Dec. 1873 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 1874-June 1874 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes insurance contracts for the various properties that Blood owned in Ithaca
    - July 1874-June 1875 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - July 1875-Dec. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes insurance contracts for the various properties that Blood owned and for the First Presbyterian Church in Ithaca; includes a congratulatory letter concerning Blood's election to the command of the 28th Brigade
    - 1876 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1877 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1878 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes letters to and from Dr. White addressing Blood's concerns about the lack of a minister at the Presbyterian Church in Ithaca
    - Jan. 1879-June 1879 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes a letter to Dr. White concerning the search for a new minister in Ithaca; includes insurance contracts for the First Presbyterian Church
    - July 1879-Dec. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes a letter ( Dec. 1879 ) sent from Berlin by Willard Fiske; letter requests a suit to be sent and it addresses A.D. White's visit to Germany
    - Jan. 1880-June 1880 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes a letter written by Mr. Hawes from the Department of State in Washington regarding a suit of clothes; includes a letter from Willard Fiske written from Berlin thanking Blood for sending the suit he had requested
    - June 1880-Dec. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes Blood's business card as a merchant tailor and a dealer in cloths
    - 1881 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Includes a letter ( May 1881 ) written by Charles H., the son of Charles F.; son addresses what the family has been doing in Ithaca during his father's absence, includes another letter (Sept. 1881) from Charles H. to his father; addresses Jennie McGraw's arrival in Ithaca and the fact that she is staying in Prof. Fiske's father's house; includes a member's card from the Bible and Prayer Union of 1882
    - Jan. 1882- June 1882 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes a letter ( Feb. 1882 ) from the Board of Home Missions requesting Blood's help in securing funds from the Presbyterian churches in the Ithaca area
    - July 1882- Dec. 1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes a letter ( Nov. 1882 ) from Charles H. and Estella (Charles F.'s wife) written to Charles F. during his trip to the West
    - Jan. 1883- June 1883 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - July 1883-June 1884 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - July 1884- Dec. 1884 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes a card ( Oct. 1884 ) designating Blood as the delegate from his church to the Synod of New York; includes a letter ( Dec. 1884 ) from Charles H. to his father; he writes about his experiences in New York City where he is staying to see a doctor
    - Jan. 1885- June 1885 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - July 1885- Dec. 1885 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Jan. 1886- June 1886 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - July 1886- Dec. 1886 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Jan. 1887- June 1887 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - July 1887- Dec. 1887 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes a letter (July 1887) from Mr. Marsh informing Blood of his membership in the Committee of the Society for the Prevention of Crime; includes a letter (Sept. 1887) from Mr. Storms informing Blood of his unanimous election to the Ithaca Savings Bank's Board of Trustees; includes a letter (Dec. 1887) from Charles H. to his father regarding business matters
    - Jan. 1888- June 1888 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - July 1888- Oct. 1888 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Nov. 1888- Dec. 1888 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 1889- Apr. 1889 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - May 1889- Aug. 1889 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Sept. 1889- Dec. 1889 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 1890- Apr. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - May 1890- Aug. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Includes a letter ( June 1890 ) from Charles H. to his father; talks about his visit to New York and his experiences at a Cornell/Yale crew race
    - Sept. 1890- Oct. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Oct. 1890- Nov. 1890 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Dec. 1890 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 1891- June 1891 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes a letter ( Jan. 1891 ) from the Town and Gown Club indicating Blood's membership
    - July 1891-Dec. 1891 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 1892- June 1892 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - July 1892- Dec. 1892 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes a certificate ( Nov. 1892 ) that contains President Harrison's Thanksgiving Proclamation
    - 1893 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1896 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1897 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous correspondences (not dated) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous correspondences (not dated) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous papers (not dated) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Printed Items
    - Not dated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1853-1866 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Includes a program ( Dec. 1866 ) from the dedication of Cornell Library where Ezra Cornell and A.D. White gave addresses
    - 1867 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1868-1874 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Includes a program ( July 1869 ) from Cornell's First Annual Commencement; includes a program ( June 1871 ) from Cornell's Class Day exercises
    - 1875-1888 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Includes a program ( June 1878 ) from Cornell's Class Day exercises; R.H. Treman is listed as the Vice-President of the class
    - 1889-1891 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Includes Cornell President Charles Adams' annual report for the year 1890-91
    - 1891-1894 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Includes the Founder's Day oration of Jan. 1893 which gives a biography of Ezra Cornell
    - 1895-1898 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Not dated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Includes pamphlets from Southern California providing information for prospective investors and migrants
    - Miscellaneous business cards, checks and papers (not dated) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Account books and documents regarding the Presbyterian Church of Ithaca
    - Documents concerning Simeon DeWitt's sale of property to the Trustees of the South Presbyterian Church of Ithaca, 1816-1826 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Two volumes of account books, 1857-1873 (Box 6)
    - One account book volume, 1883-1884 (Box 6)
- Series II. Charles H. Blood
  - Correspondence and other manuscript items
    - Aug. 16, 1889- Sept. 25, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 9, 1896- June 30, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - July 2, 1896- Dec. 28, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 4, 1897- Aug. 14, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Jan. 8, 1898- May 14, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - May 17, 1898- June 30, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - July 1, 1898- Sept. 15, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Sept. 16, 1898- Oct. 28, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Nov. 1, 1898- Dec. 5, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Includes several items ( Nov. 1898 ) from a man who is offering Blood an opportunity to make money in the illegal business of duplicate bills; includes a letter ( Nov. 1898 ) that announces his election to the Board of Trustees of the Ithaca Savings Bank following the death of his father who formerly held the position
    - Dec. 7, 1898- Dec. 30, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Includes a letter ( Dec. 1898 ) from George Priest requesting an endorsement letter from Blood to be sent to Governor-elect Theodore Roosevelt
    - Jan. 1, 1899- Mar. 11, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Includes a letter ( Jan. 1899 ) from George Priest thanking Blood for writing a recommendation letter to New York Governor Theodore Roosevelt
    - Mar. 17, 1899- May 5, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - May 6, 1899- July 15, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      Includes a letter ( May 1899 ) from Edward Gladding regarding divorce laws and the equality of women
    - July 17, 1899- Dec. 26, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      Includes a letter ( Nov. 1899 ) from Blood to the Editor of the Buffalo Evening News (E.H. Butler) concerning the drowning of Edward Berkeley at Cornell
    - Apr. 16, 1900- Mar. 24, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Mar. 25, 1902- Apr. 14, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Apr. 16, 1902- Apr. 30, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Includes a letter ( Apr. 21, 1902 ) from Blood to Mrs. Lang discussing her divorce and the evidence needed to secure a divorce
    - May 1, 1902- May 24, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - June 3, 1902- July 15, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - July 14, 1902- July 31, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Aug. 1, 1902- Aug. 30, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Sept. 1, 1902- Sept. 29, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Oct. 1, 1902- Oct. 15, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Includes a letter ( Oct. 1902 ) from The Alumni Athletic Field Committee regarding the presentation of their athletic field project at the next meeting of the Cornell trustees
    - Oct. 16, 1902- Nov. 13, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Includes letters ( Oct. 1902 ) from Cornell President J.G. Schurman
    - Nov. 16, 1902- Dec. 9, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Includes letters ( Nov. 1902 ) from J.G. Schurman; one states that he is going to recommend a location for the new athletic field at Cornell; includes a newspaper clipping regarding Blood's actions in the Churchill murder trial
    - Feb. 3, 1903- Dec. 19, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Includes several sheets about the typhoid epidemic in 1903
    - Jan. 4, 1906- Jan. 29, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Feb. 2, 1906- Feb. 22, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Includes a letter ( Feb. 6, 1906 ) from President Schurman informing Blood of the itinerary planned for the Imperial Chinese Commissioners' visit to Cornell; includes several letters regarding Blood's re-election as a Cornell trustee
    - Feb. 23, 1906- Mar. 15, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Includes letters from various people in different states endorsing Blood's re-election to the Board of Trustees
    - Mar. 16, 1906- Apr. 10, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Includes a pamphlet outlining the nomination of Blood for Cornell Trustee for the election of June 1906
    - Apr. 11, 1906- Apr. 14, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Apr. 18, 1906- May 10, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Includes several letters ( May 1906 ) from President Schurman regarding the landscape of the Cornell campus and the placement of a new road
    - May 12, 1906- May 25, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Includes a pamphlet about the possibility of allowing library books to circulate into homes; includes a statement made by A.D. White about his opinion on circulating books; includes a map ( 1900 ) of the Cornell University campus
    - May 26, 1906- June 5, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Includes a letter ( May 1906 ) from President Schurman regarding the use of Fall Creek gorge for water power
    - June 6, 1906- June 20, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Includes various information about the Cornell reunions on June 20, 1906
    - June 21, 1906- July 31, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Includes letters ( June 1906 ) from President Schurman including one regarding a report written by Blood
    - Aug. 1, 1906- Aug. 29, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Sept. 1, 1906- Sept. 20, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Sept. 21, 1906- Oct. 15, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Oct. 16, 1906- Oct. 31, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Includes several letters from various members of the Sphinx Head Society urging Blood to support the society's request for a plot of land on Cornell's campus. Blood was a member of the Quill and Dagger Society.
    - Nov. 1, 1906- Nov. 29, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Includes several letters from various members of the Sphinx Head Society urging Blood to support the society's request for a plot of land on Cornell's campus
    - Dec. 1, 1906- Dec. 20, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Dec. 21, 1906- Dec. 29, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Apr. 5, 1907- July 31, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Includes Blood's biography for the 1907 edition of Who's Who in New York City and State
    - Aug. 10, 1908- Dec. 16, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous papers (not dated) (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous papers (not dated) (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous correspondences (not dated) (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Letterbooks of outgoing correspondence
    - Eight volumes from 1897-1909 (Box 10)
  - Various books
    - Law text with lecture synopsis and notes by Blood, 1888-1890 (Box 11)
    - Scribble book, 1910 (Box 11)
    - Synopsis of lectures given by Blood at Cornell University Law School, 1898 (Box 11)
    - Notes on real property (not dated) (Box 11)